Southwest Institute for Research on Women Records, circa 1885, 1970-2001 (bulk 1979-2000)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Southwest Institute for Research on Women Records circa 1885, 1970-2001 (bulk 1979-2000)
MS 518
Southwest Institute for Research on Women (U.S.)
This collection is comprised of documents, photographs, and audio/visual materials of the Southwest Institute for Research on Women (SIROW), which is a research and resource center for women and girls. The bulk of the material consists of: essays, ephemeral material, newspaper clippings, administrative material, grants, correspondence, and cassette tapes. Topics include an array of different subjects relating to women’s studies, including: education, economy, cultural diversity, literature & film, and community outreach.
3.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions for this collection.
Historical Note
The Southwest Institute for Research on Women is a research and resource center focusing on the lives of women and girls of the Southwest. SIROW was founded in 1979 in Tucson, Arizona and is part of the Women’s Studies Department at the University of Arizona. Its primary focus is intended for parts of the Southwestern region of the U.S., including: Arizona, Colorado, Nevada, New Mexico, West Texas, Utah, Wyoming, and the Northwestern Mexico border. The Southwest Institute for Research on Women has become a regional network for over 30 campuses within the Southwest region.
SIROW’s mission is to “develop, conduct, and disseminate collaborative research, education and outreach projects of importance to diverse groups of women and girls in the Southwestern United States and Northwestern Mexico” (2012 SIROW Annual Report).
Arrangement
This collection is organized into eight series.
Series I: Writings 1981-1997
Series II: Publicity 1971-2000
Series III: Correspondence 1975-1996
Series IV: Administrative 1970-1998
Series V: Grants, Reports, and Proposals 1979-1996
Series VI: Photographs circa 1885-2000
Series VII: Audio/Visual 1977-1993
Series VIII: Oversize Materials 1998-2000
Scope and Content Note
Materials that hone in on women’s studies are the primary focus for this collection. This collection is largely comprised of writings, newspaper clippings, administrative material, and ephemeral material related to or associated with the Southwest Institute for Research on Women (SIROW). This collection also includes: books, video tapes, and oversize materials. The dates of this collection are mostly comprised of late 20th century material; however, some of the photographs within this collection are dated from the late 19th century.
Access Terms
University of Arizona
Women’s Studies
Women’s Studies- Organizations
Southwest-Women’s Studies-Organizations
Women’s Studies-Institute
Women’s Research
Container List
- Series I: Writings, 1981-1997
  - Subseries 1: Working Papers, 1981-1994
    Working Paper #32 is missing.
    - Working Papers No.1-4, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Working Papers No.5-8, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Working Papers No.9-12, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Working Papers No.13-16, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Working Papers No.17-20, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Working Papers No.21-24, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Working Papers No.25-28, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Working Papers No.29-31,33, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 2: Occasional Papers, 1981-1997
    This subseries is arranged numerically. Occasional Papers #6 and #12 are missing.
    - Occasional Papers No.1-4, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Occasional Papers No.5-7, 1986, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Occasional Papers No.8-10, 1989, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Occasional Papers No.11, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Occasional Papers No.13-16, 1992-1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 3: Other Essays, 1986-1994
    This subseries is arranged by title.
    - Women’s Employment in Changing Nonmetropolitan Economies, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Safe Womanhood: A Discussion Paper, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - If Women Leave the Home, What are Men to do, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 4: Books, 1981-1991
    - Working Papers of the Arizona Board of Regents’ Commission on the Status of Women, 1981-1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Curriculum Resources in Chicano Studies, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - The Importance of Teaching, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series II: Publicity 1971-2001
  - Subseries 1: Newsletters & Magazines, 1979-1999
    This subseries is arranged numerically. (SIROW Newsletter #36 is missing)
    - SIROW Newsletter No.1-25, 1979-1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - SIROW Newsletter No.26-45, 1986-1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - SIROW Newsletter No.46-58, 1993-1999 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Accent on Mathematics Engineering & Science (AMES), 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Arizona Insight, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Office of International Programs (OIP), 1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Women’s Studies Advisory Council (WOSAC), 1999 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - MEMO Newsletter, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Diversity Digest, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Outreach UA, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Arizona Books for Spring, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Connections (For Equal Vocational Opportunities), 1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Arizona Chamber Executives, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 2: Newspaper Clippings, 1971-2000
    This subseries is arranged by subject.
    - Women’s Studies, 1973, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Science & Engineering, 1971-1996 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Making Math Count, 1990-1996 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Rhodes Scholarship at the U of A, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Cultural Diversity at the U of A, 1987-1996 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Building Across Borders, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Community Outreach Project on Aids in Southern Arizona (COPASA), 1996-2000 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - The Lady Takes the Wheel, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Daughters of the Desert, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - The Desert is No Lady, 1995-1998 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Their Land, Their Lives, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Women & the Economy, 1986-1997 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Jan Monk, 1993-2000 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Gail Parker, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Sarah Weddington, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Subseries 3: Ephemera, 1975-2000
    - Women's Studies & SIROW, 1980-1998 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Women's Studies Conferences, 1975-2000 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - The Desert is No Lady, 1995-1998 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - The Lady Takes the Wheel, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Daughters of the Desert, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Their Land, Their Lives, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Science, Technology, & Engineering, 1977-1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - National Council of La Raza, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - The Transborder Consortium, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Gail Parker, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Sarah Weddington, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Community Outreach, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Series III: Correspondence (Letters, E-mails, & Fax), 1975-1996
  This series is arranged by subject.
  - SIROW General, 1992-1996 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Women’s Studies Curriculum Committee, 1977-1988 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - SIROW Funding, 1981-1994 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Gail Parker, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Rita Marko, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Ann Brigham, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Marta Civil & Math Programs, 1990-1996 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - The Thanks to be a Grandmother Winifred Foundation, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Breast Feeding Project, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - The Desert is No Lady, 1992-1996 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Chicana Literature: A Discourse on Identity, 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Social Influences on the Participation on Mexican American Women in Science, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Series IV: Administrative (Notes, Contact Information, Schedules, Minutes, Financial Agreements, etc.) 1970-1998
  - SIROW & Women's Studies, 1980-1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - SIROW Visiting Scholars, 1985-1988 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Transborder Consortium, 1970-1998 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Social Influences on the Participation of Mexican American Women in Science, 1980-1987 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Breast Feeding Project Meeting, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Gail Parker, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - The Desert is No Lady Finance Agreements, 1992-1994 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Marta Civil & Math Programs, 1990-1997 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series V: Grants, Reports, & Proposals 1979-1996
  This series is arranged by subject. This series includes various grants, project reports, and proposals for: SIROW, research projects, and academia.
  - SIROW Projects, 1989-1996 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Science Education Programs in Faculty of Science (U of A), 1989 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Western States Project on Women in the Curriculum, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Western Women: Their Land, Their Lives, 1983-1985 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Making Math Count: A Training Program for Middle School Math Teachers, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Chicana Literature, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Proposal for SIROW (1st & 2nd), 1979-1982 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Proposal for Research Project: Social Influences on Participation of Mexican American Women in Science, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Proposal for an Undergraduate Major in Women’s Studies, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Grant Applications, 1982-1996 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Series VI: Photographs circa 1885-2000
  This series is arranged by subject. The photographs that are contained within the “People & Places of the Southwest” folders are dated from the 1880s to the 1980s, but primarily consist of the late 1800s. There is only one photograph that is dated in the 1980s which also contains negatives. The photographs contained within the folder titled, “SIROW & Women’s Studies” are dated from the 1980’s to 2000. Lastly, the photograph from the production “Stories from the Bloodhut” is not dated.
  - People & Places of the Southwest, circa 1885-1961 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - People & Places of the Southwest, circa 1890-1981 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - SIROW & Women’s Studies, 1987-1998 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - SIROW & Women's Studies, 1998-2000 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - SIROW & Women's Studies, 1998-2000 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - SIROW & Women's Studies, circa 1998-2000 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Stories from the Bloodhut, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Series VII: Audio/Visual 1977-1993
  The audio/visual series is comprised of videotapes and cassette tapes. The videotapes are arranged numerically. The audio cassette series is arranged by date, partial date, and no date. This series includes subjects such as: gender & society, feminist theory, women & justice, language & literature, feminism & national security, women & politics, race & class, Hispanic literature, women & film, women writers, Western Women Conference, and National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) meetings.
  - Videotapes-Making Worlds Conference (Master #1), 1993 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Videotapes- Making Worlds Conference (Master #2), 1993 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Cassette Tapes, November 7, 1977-June 22, 1983 (Box 8)
  - Cassette Tapes, June 22, 1983-November 19, 1984 (Box 9)
  - Cassette Tapes, November 26, 1984-March 17, 1987 (Box 10)
  - Cassette Tapes, 1988, undated, January 17, 1988- Western Women Conference (tapes 1-24) (Box 11)
  - Cassette Tapes, This series is arranged by partial dates & no dates. (Box 12)
- Series VIII: Oversize Materials 1998-2000
  This series includes Transborder Consortium “major flyers”, proofs, and negatives.
  - Transborder Consortium, 1998-2000 (Box 13, Folder 1)